בוקר
טוב, Boker tov, good ערב שבועות, erev Shavuos, 49th day of the
עומר. Omer. Today is we're on דף קכ״ט Daf Kof Chaf Tes
129. We pick up four lines from the top, five lines from
the top, המחלק נכסיו על פיו. Hamechalek nechasav al pi. Thank you.
Nice jacket there, Michael.
Okay, so this is we're finally moving into the territory of a
person who is the מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas Shachiv Mera, who is
giving a deathbed division of property and it speaks but and we're
saying that if he divides it as a type of a gift
and working within the rabbinic institution of this מתנת שכיב מרע matnas
Shachiv Mera that's fine, but if he tries to reassign a ירושה,
yerusha, it's no good because the ירושה yerusha is the way the
תורה Torah defined it. So he can't say I'm giving you a
bigger portion of the ירושה. yerusha. And then the
משנה Mishna though however said that, sorry, that we are inclined to
try to read everything possibly as a legitimate מתנה matana which you
know just once again shows how much we are on the one
hand, you know, there's a whole point in the תורה Torah
that this person cannot change the בכור bechor and he cannot give
the בכור bechor to a younger son and then on the other
hand the rabbis through these rabbinic institutions, you know, sort of like
you know like היתר עיסקא heter iska and whatever, you know, and
פרוזבול pruzbul or whatever basically find a way to do exactly that
and to radically redistribute it
as long as the person is giving it as a gift and
they've even made it easier to give this gift, a verbal type
of a מתנת שכיב מרע matnas Shachiv Mera and not only that,
the משנה Mishna says that even if it sounds like he's trying
to do a ירושה yerusha if there's the word of
מתנה matana anywhere in the declaration we're going to use the word
מתנה matana to interpret it as a gift. Okay so that's what
it says.
Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. המחלק נכסיו על פיו Hamechalek nechasav al pi read to
one or little to another, if it's a ירושה yerusha it's not
good, if it's מתנה matana it's good
whether the language of מתנה matana appeared in the beginning, middle or
end. So the גמרא Gemara says היכי דמי מתנה בתחילה היכי דמי
באמצע היכי דמי בסוף. Heichi dami matana bit-chila heichi dami ba'emtza heichi
dami basof. What's an example of saying the word מתנה matana in
the beginning, an example of saying it in the middle and an
example of saying it at the end?
And how much can the dominance theme really sound like ירושה yerusha
and it still be good? So excuse
me.
Yeah, I know. So anyway we're based on this גמרא Gemara so
כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן ki ata Rav Dimi amar
Rabi Yochanan
when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he
said in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan תינתן
שדה פלונית לפלוני ויירשה tinasen sadeh plonis l'ploni v'yirshah sorry man, let
this field be given to ראובן Reuven and let him inherit it
זו
היא מתנה בתחילה zu hi matana bit-chila that's saying מתנה matana at
the beginning. So even though you would think at the end he
said and let him inherit it and that should define the nature
of what he's doing, no, since he said at the beginning give
it to him that defines it,
that is sufficient to define it as a gift and it's binding.
Okay. יירשה ותינתן לו yirsha v'sinasen lo let ראובן Reuven inherit this
field and give it to him okay זו היא מתנה בסוף zu
hi matana basof that's saying מתנה matana at the end and that
works. יירשה ותינתן לו ויירשה yirsha v'sinasen lo v'yirshah Michael can you
go get some paper towels for me or something? Sorry. You know
where they are? No I don't know but if you just get
paper towels from the bathroom thank you.
Okay
that's מתנה בתחילה. matana bit-chila. Sorry. Oh
man okay. Okay so okay so זו
היא מתנה בסוף. zu hi matana basof. יירשה yirsha that's מתנה matana
at the end. יירשה ותינתן לו ויירשה yirsha v'sinasen lo v'yirshah let
him inherit it and give it to him and let him inherit
it so you think saying let him inherit it three times twice
beginning and the thank you beginning and the end that would define
it as a ירושה yerusha no זו היא מתנה באמצע zu hi
matana ba'emtza that's saying מתנה matana in the middle and all of
that works no matter how dominant it is
that he sounds like he's trying to do a ירושה yerusha as
long as you've got the magic word מתנה matana in there somewhere
it works. Okay one minute ודווקא באדם אחד ושדה אחד v'davka b'adam
echad v'sadeh echad that's only if your statement refers to one field
and one person that we're willing to take the word מתנה matana
and say that it defines the entirety of what you're doing. However
אבל באדם אחד ושני שדות aval b'adam echad u-shnei sados
let's say it's one person and two fields you say give ראובן
Reuven my you know my you know my field on you know
on Central Park and let him inherit my field you know my
house on Riverside. Okay so there we don't say oh he said
give for one so everything is a gift. No the one in
Central Park is a gift and that works and the one on
Riverside is a ירושה yerusha and that doesn't work. Okay so one
person and two fields using a different word for each one you
don't make it one you don't make it one. don't have the
word מתנה matanah define everything. The word מתנה matanah only defines the
field that it's in reference to. Okay, אדם אחד ושתי שדות. Adam
echad v'shtei sadot. Now, שדה אחד ושני בני אדם, Sadeh echad u'shnei
bnei Adam, let's say you say, "Oh, my nice house there on
Central Park, you know, give it to ראובן Reuven and let שמעון
Shimon inherit it." All right, so you don't say, "Oh, well he
said give it to one of those people, so it's a gift
for both." No, for ראובן Reuven it's a gift and it works,
and for שמעון Shimon it's a ירושה yerushah and it doesn't work.
So ראובן Reuven is the only one who gets it. Now, does
ראובן Reuven get half of it or does he get all of
it? It's not clear. Okay, but therefore, as long as there's a
way to split it, either because I'm using a different verb for
the for different people or I'm using a different verb for for
the different different plots of land, then we don't say, so to
say, that the word מתנה matanah defines everything. The word מתנה matanah
only defines the person and the plot of land who it was
said in reference to. Yes. Is this, is this, I totally, I
totally don't understand what ever- everything we've already learned here. We haven't
even seen רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. You're running ahead. Okay, okay, but
my question is, how does this, I mean, he doesn't- of course,
yeah, go ahead. When we say פשט רישא, פשט סיפא, pshat resha,
pshat seifa, right, so we- correct, and that's exactly what you said,
it's what I was being saying all along, that the Rabbis really
wanted to give a person a lot more latitude than the Torah
seems to give them. They created this whole institution of מתנת שכיב
מרע, matnat shchiv mera, and therefore they're just doing everything we can
to try to make it work, you know? Clearly there was a
pressing societal need, I mean, it just shows you how radical it
is what the Rabbis are doing. If it's מתנת שכיב מרע, matnat
shchiv mera, does it, like, you know, let's say you say it
when you're per- the next second you drop dead. You're not a
שכיב מרע, shchiv mera, you're like, shot dead, you know? But he-
but he did it with a קנין? kinyan? Yeah.
Well, if a person did it with a קנין, kinyan, then that's
an interesting question. What if this was done through a קנין kinyan
and not in the context of a מתנת שכיב מרע, matnat shchiv
mera, would we say the same thing? I imagine we would, but
nevertheless, it's to achieve the same point, so, you know, the Rabbis
just want to really give the person this power, this latitude. I
don't know what else to say. Well, then you see this as
a general, you know, challenge to any of these other opinions about
פשט רישא pshat resha and פשט סיפא? pshat seifa? No, no, here
clearly there's a larger agenda here. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, so that's one, we're willing to interpret the word מתנה
matanah but as long as we're not splitting, you know, different different
things are happening for different people or for different fields. Okay, that's
what the first position says in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, now רבי- רבי אלעזר Rabbi-
Rabbi Elazar says, אפילו אדם אחד ושתי שדות, afillu adam echad v'shtei
sadot, שדה אחד ושני בני אדם. sadeh echad v'shnei bnei adam. No,
no, no, no, even if it's one person and two fields. Let
ראובן Reuven get my house on Central Park West and let him-
and let him inherit the one on Riverside. Up, since by ראובן
Reuven you used the word give, so that applies to both houses
even though by the Riverside you said let him inherit it. Okay,
that'll work because at least you're giving two things to ראובן Reuven
and one of them you said give, so it applies to both.
Okay, that's אדם אחד ושתי שדות. adam echad v'shtei sadot. Or שני
בני אדם, shnei bnei adam,
where I lost my place? ושתי-
ושדה אחד ושני בני אדם. v'shtei- v'sadeh echad v'shnei bnei adam. Or
let ראובן, Reuven, you know, give ראובן Reuven my house on Central
Park West and let שמעון Shimon inherit it. So, since you're talking
about the same house and for one of them you said give,
then the give applies to both people. Okay, so as long as
there's some common thing, either the same person or the same plot
of land, we'll interpret the word give to apply to everything. However,
אבל
בשתי שדות בשני בני אדם, aval b'shtei sadot b'shnei bnei adam, let
ראובן Reuven get- give ראובן Reuven my house on Central Park West
and let שמעון Shimon inherit my house in on River- on Riverside,
okay, that, clearly there's nothing common between them. So we say the
ראובן Reuven thing works and the שמעון Shimon thing doesn't work. לא,
lo, that doesn't work. Okay, even though they were all said in
the same sentence, but there's nothing in the gift itself that's common.
That's רבי אלעזר'ס Rabbi Elazar's position. כי אתא רבין אמר, Ki ata
Ravin amar, now when רבין Ravin came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
he said, תנתן שדה פלונית לפלוני ויירש פלונית שדה פלונית, tinaten sadeh
plonit l'ploni v'yirash plonit sadeh plonit, exactly this case. Give the the
house on Central Park to ראובן Reuven and let שמעון Shimon inherit
the house in on River- on Riverside, it says שדה, sadeh, I'm
making it a house, anyway, so different people, different plots of land
with one you use לשון מתנה, lashon matanah, with one you use
לשון ירושה, lashon yerushah, what we said now everybody would agree that
you have to split that and you can't use מתנה matanah for
the other thing, so here he actually says that actually רבי יוחנן
אמר קנה. Rabbi Yochanan amar kanah. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan actually says
it does work. So before we had, if you remember, right above,
רב דימי Rav Dimi said in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan that it had to be completely the same person and the
same field to work. Here we're saying even two people and two
different fields, if you know, you take one the word of מתנה
matanah for one and you apply it to the other. Okay, so
here רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it works. רבי אליעזר אומר לא
קנה. Rabbi Eliezer omer lo kanah. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says no,
come on, two different people and two different fields, it does not
work. All right, so אמר אביי לרבין, amar Abaye l'Ravin, so, here
this might just get a little bit confused here cause we're at
three positions, okay? So you have
רב דימי Rav Dimi says that according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
if it's Basically it's only if it's it only works if it's
same field and same person.
And according to רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
either
same field
or same person.
That's רב דימי. Rav Dimi. And then this is רבין, Ravin, okay,
so yeah that'll be רב דימי. Rav Dimi. רב דימי. Rav Dimi.
Now comes along רבין, Ravin, it's רבין, Ravin, right? I got that
right? רבין Ravin says according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, you know,
the exact opposite basically. Even if different field
and different person, it works.
The exact opposite. And רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar he said different field
and different person,
no. I mean everything else is yes,
okay? I mean that's when it does work, okay? This is when
it doesn't. Now, okay, so here basically this contradicts. It has to
be the same field and the same person. This is even the
different field and a different person, right? So that's the exact opposite.
Do these two versions of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar disagree? Either the
same field or the same person it works, different field and different
person it doesn't work. Do those disagree?
No, they're the same part, right? If one is the same it
works, if they're both different it doesn't work. Okay, so רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar is going to work, these two versions of רבי אלעזר.
Rabbi Elazar. They're the same two different halves of the same statement,
okay? Whereas this, right, is saying actually diametrically opposite things. Okay, so
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. Oh, you can tell from the
second point you don't know what אלעזר Elazar holds about the first.
Correct. Okay, so but they don't contradict they support each other. Correct.
Correct. Okay, so complementary. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר
ליה אביי לרבין. Amar leh Abaye le-Ravin. So אביי Abaye said to
רבין: Ravin: אנחסת לן חדא. An-chasat lan chada.
One thing we can be deal with with what you said, it's
good with us. ואטקפת לן חדא. Ve-atkafat lan chada. But one thing
you said is very difficult for us. בשלמא Bishlama דרבי אלעזר דרבי
אלעזר לא קשיא. de-Rabbi Elazar de-Rabbi Elazar lo kashya. The two statements
of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, you know, רב דימי's Rav Dimi version
and your version are not difficult. כאן באדם אחד ושתי שדות כאן
בשני בני אדם ושתי שדות. Kan be-adam echad u-shtei sadot, kan be-shnei
benei adam u-shtei sadot.
That when רבין's Ravin version that it worked was
one person two fields or two people one field, that's when it
does work. When you're saying רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says it doesn't
work, that's when it's two people and two fields. Those completely complement,
okay? Yes, Gloria, you got it? Okay.
אבל Aval דרבי יוחנן דרבי יוחנן קשיא. de-Rabbi Yochanan de-Rabbi Yochanan kashya.
But רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, here you're saying you need them both
to be the same, and here you're saying even when they're both
different. Okay, the exact diametrically opposed position. So the גמרא Gemara says:
אמוראי נינהו ואליבא דרבי יוחנן. Amora'ei ninhu ve-aliba de-Rabbi Yochanan. Yeah,
guess what? That's exactly it. רב דימי's Rav Dimi version of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is that only if they're both the same and
רבין's Ravin version of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is even if they're
both different. These אמוראים Amora'im take diametrically opposed positions of רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. Okay. רב דימי's Rav Dimi version was taking his good
notes. Yeah. Right. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says: You need both. That's
what he said. So why do I have this you need both
for it to be good? No, actually no actually you need both
wouldn't work. Both! So what's oh, you need both for it to
be good and the other said even if you have both it's
okay. Even if even if both are whatever the opposite. Anyway, moving
on. Okay, anyway. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אמר: amar: לא קנה Lo
kana when they're different people and different fields, it'll only work if
meaning he's basically saying different people and different fields doesn't work.
But if you want it to work with different people and different
fields, here's the formula you have to say. לא קנה עד שיאמר:
Lo kana ad she-yomar: פלוני ופלוני יירשו שדה פלונית ופלונית. Peloni u-peloni
yirshu sdeh pelonit u-pelonit. Let ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon inherit the
you know, this particular field. פלוני
ופלוני יירשו שדה פלונית ופלונית. Peloni u-peloni yirshu sdeh pelonit u-pelonit. Let
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon inherit the the house on you know
on Central Park and the one on Riverside. שנתתים להם במתנה ויירשום.
She-natatim lahem be-matanah ve-yirshum. That I have given them as a מתנה
matanah as a gift and ויירשום ve-yirshum and let them inherit it.
Okay. So somehow because I am so even though I'm talking about
two different people and two different fields, although you could say it's
not clear. It sounds like maybe normally two different people two different
fields is ראובן Reuven gets field A and שמעון Shimon gets field
B. Here it sounds like he's giving ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon
both A and B, right? So therefore you might be inclined to
say that that's more likely to work. But anyway, ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says you have to sort of like package it all together.
You have to say at the beginning ירושה, yerusha, at the end
ירושה, yerusha, מתנה matanah in the middle.
So it's not exactly clear. There's a long רשב"ם Rashbam that figures
out like variations of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. But what is clear
is that according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, fundamentally two people and
two fields doesn't work unless you find a way to like package
it all tightly together to make it one unit. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר רב... Amar Rav... yes sure. Yeah
Gloria.
Right. And one of them is an effective term and one is
not, right? Is there anything that says, if all he does, he's
a שכיב מרע shachiv meira doing it, and all he does is
says מתנה, matanah, that then of... Right. Yeah, then of course, absolutely.
Right, the whole thing is because he says the bad word for
one of them and we have to get the good word, we
want to borrow the good word and make it work for the
part, for the person for whom he didn't say it for. But
if he just says a לשון מתנה, lashon matanah, then of course,
then everything works, right? Yeah, absolutely. This is all because we have
to get around the bad term of ירושה yerushah that he used.
Yeah. I was just going to
say,
why is he using that word ירושה yerushah at all if he
knows what he's wanting to do? Right. So, because he, because, yeah,
he wants this, this is his deathbed bequest, he wants, in his
mind, it's what he's bequeathing in a ירושה, yerushah, but somebody said
to him, "Hey, if you know, if you want it to be
legally binding, you have to frame it as a gift. You can't
frame it as a ירושה." yerushah. Okay, that's what the lawyer friend
is telling this guy. But in his head, he's thinking ירושה. yerushah.
So he's not being a lawyer when he's saying this term. He's
expressing what he feels about them. And that's why the ירושה yerushah
term keeps on popping up, you know? Okay. If he was a
שכיב מרע? shachiv meira?
Well, that's what Mike asked before. The classic case is this is
a שכיב מרע, shachiv meira, and on the deathbed even the verbal
gift works. If it's not a שכיב מרע shachiv meira and he
does it with an act of a קנין, kinyan, like through like
a handkerchief or whatever, then it could work as well. Okay? If
he happens to use these two phrases and it's not a שכיב
מרע? shachiv meira? If he's just, he's not a שכיב מרע shachiv
meira and he just wants to say, "I'm giving." He can do
it that way, right? And then that's... Sure, but then it's not
legally binding. If it, for it to be legally binding, it either
has to be on his deathbed or it has to be with
a קנין, kinyan, with like a, you know, an act of a
קנין kinyan like with a handkerchief or whatever. Okay? Yeah, I mean,
you can say whatever you want. Now there is a different category
called מצוה לקיים דברי המת, mitzvah lekayem divrei hameis, which is that
the act, the words, you know, were not, did not have the
effect of law, they didn't transfer the property itself because it wasn't
done in the right context. A guy wasn't on his deathbed, okay,
but before he, I don't know, got on a plane, he said
something and he said, you know, you know, if the, you know,
if I don't make it back, whatever, do x, y, and z,
and then he didn't make it back, right? So that's not a
deathbed, it's not binding, but there's an idea that the heirs have
a moral responsibility to fulfill the last wishes of their, of their
father or whatever, of the one who passed away. Or if he
had a will, right? Even if it's not הלכתית halachically binding? Right.
But then, okay, he dies. Yeah, that would be מצוה לקיים דברי
המת. mitzvah lekayem divrei hameis. Okay, that you, that there's an idea
to do the wishes of the person, but that's not, that doesn't
have the legal force of affecting a transfer of property. If you
want this to affect the transfer of property, it either has to
be with a קנין kinyan or like on the deathbed. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
Now, בפלוגתא, beplugta, this, this debate here about these three possibilities, right?
The three possibilities are they both have to be the same, one
has to be the same, or even if they're both different, is,
it's a parallel to another, you know, the same debate we have
elsewhere. אמר רב המנונא, Amar Rav Hamnuna, says רב המנונא, Rav Hamnuna,
אדם אחד ושתי שדות... Adam echad ushtei sadot... sorry, just messed up.
לא שנו אלא אדם אחד ושדה אחת. Lo shanu ela adam echad
vesadeh achas. When does it work that you can use the מתנה
matanah language for everything? If it's one person, one field. אבל אדם
אחד ושתי שדות, שדה אחת ושני בני אדם, Aval adam echad ushtei
sadot, sadeh achas ushnei bnei adam, but if either it's two fields
or two people, לא, lo, it doesn't work. That is רב דימי'ס
Rav Dimi's version of ר' יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. רב נחמן אמר אפילו
אדם אחד ושתי שדות, שדה אחת ושני בני אדם. Rav Nachman amar
afilu adam echad ushtei sadot, sadeh achas ushnei bnei adam. No, as
long as one thing is the same. Either it's one person and
two fields or two people and one field, the לשון מתנה lashon
matanah works for everything. אבל שתי שדות ושני בני אדם, Aval shtei
sadot ushnei bnei adam, but two people and two fields with the
language of שדה sadeh for one and of מתנה matanah for one
and ירושה yerushah for the other, that does not work. לא. Lo.
That's everybody's version of ר' אלעזר. Rebbi Elazar. לא. Lo. ורב ששת
אמר, Verav Sheshes amar, now רב ששת Rav Sheshes says, אפילו שתי
שדות ושני בני אדם, afilu shtei sadot ushnei bnei adam, even two
fields and two people, we will use the language of מתנה matanah
that you used for one to apply to the other. רבין'ס Rabin's
version of ר' יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. Okay. אמר רב ששת מנא אמינא
לה, Amar Rav Sheshes mana amina lah, where do I see the
idea that you can borrow a language of מתנה matanah even with
a different person and a different field and apply it in order
to make everything work? מנא אמינא לה דתניא, Mana amina lah detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא. braisa. האומר תנו שקל לבני בשבת. Ha'omer
tenu shekel livni beshabas. Now here again it's not exactly clear, what
is this person doing? Is this person saying this on his deathbed?
Is this person about to leave for a trip and he wants
to, and he's talking to the person who he's given to be
like the, what do you call it, not the executor of the
estate, but the, what's the person, what's the, what's the name of
that role that you give somebody to supervise
your, take care of, whatever? Administrator? Yeah, I guess the administrator, whatever.
Anyway, the person he's given to run his household while he's away,
and he says, "I'm going to be away, you know, provide a..."
he's setting a fund aside for his child, "provide my son with
a שקל shekel each week." שבת Shabas does not mean Shabbat. But
it's per week. Okay. Give him a weekly allowance of a שקל
shekel *shekel*. Okay. He doesn't say בשבת *BeShabbat*, he means really לשבת
*LeShabbat*. לשבת *LeShabbat*, for each week. Okay? So it's not clear if
he's saying this as a deathbed bequest or if he's saying this
as again it's just some instructions to some person who's running his...
this what do you call it? This... you know, his estate. Okay,
so give anyway a שקל shekel *shekel* which is... right an allowance,
give a weekly allowance to my son a שקל shekel. *shekel*, which
is half of a סלע *sela*. וראויין ליתן סלע *Vera'uyim litein sela*.
But actually based on, you know, the son's normal types of needs
and whatever and expenses, really, you know, and given the wealth of
this guy and the size of the estate, it really would be
more appropriate to give him a סלע *sela*, which would be twice
as much. Not 50 bucks a week but 100 bucks a week.
נותנין לו סלע *Notnin lo sela*. You give him... you give the
kid a סלע *sela*. Why is that? Because he didn't say give
him only a שקל shekel *shekel*. He said give him a שקל
shekel, *shekel*. Fine. You know, $100 is also... is also $50. Okay?
You didn't say only
a
שקל shekel *shekel*. ואם אמר אל תתנו להם אלא שקל shekel, *Ve'im
amar al titnu lahem ela shekel*. Don't give more than a שקל
shekel *shekel*. More... don't give any more than $50. אין נותנין לו
אלא שקל shekel, *Ein notnin lo ela shekel*. Then you only give,
you know, the $50. Okay? So... so
that's true. I guess you could give less if you felt that
was appropriate. But this is always an interesting question, right? What is
the latitude of the... of the you know, assuming this is like
an אפוטרופוס *apitropas*, of the executor based on how he assesses the
needs of the kids or whatever that are under his responsibility and
the estate and balancing that with the... with the you know directive
of the person who died. I remember reading a recent תשובה *teshuva*
where somebody basically said he funded a כולל *kollel* before he died.
And this goes back like 200 years. And he basically said something
like... like...
you know, all...
something like... you know all other things being equal you should give...
you know the spots on the כולל *kollel* to people that are
in my family.
Whatever. And then he died. It was a very nice כולל *kollel*,
had been very well funded, so it got a lot of good
learners. Anyway, so it had... and there were ten spots. And I'm
not making this up. This is a תשובה *teshuva*. And then everybody
was like... it had this whole כולל *kollel* full of good learners
and then somebody married this guy's I don't know daughter or granddaughter.
So he said, "Oh, you gotta kick one of those guys out
because I'm the family." And he said, "Any... all other things being
equal you should give it to a member of the family." Okay?
So... so the question was number one: does family include in-laws or
does it only mean like immediate family? And question number two was:
was that... that's gonna be terrible policy because who's gonna want to
learn in a כולל *kollel* if even if they're doing a good
job and you know they're learning up the storm as soon as
somebody marries into the family they could be kicked out, right? And
presumably what the guy meant was... you know was like if a
spot opens up, then who should you give it to? But not
that you actually kick... anyway, so what's fascinating about this תשובה *teshuva*
is how much do you sort of, you know, based on what
would be... how much is it what the guy was thinking and
how we can speculate what he probably meant? And how much do
we sort of use what would just be like good policy, you
know, to dictate how we should choose to interpret what he said?
Anyway, so just something a little parallel. What did they do? I
don't even remember. But the point is is that you know there's
like you have balancing obligations. This person's responsible for the estate, responsible
for the kids, and he has the instructions of the original person.
So in cases of ambiguity, what do you do? So in the
first case here they gave the kid what the kid needed and
what the estate could afford. In the second case where the instructions
were clearer, they didn't. Okay. אין נותנין לו אלא שקל shekel. *Ein
notnin lo ela shekel*. ואם אמר *Ve'im amar*, now he says אם
מתו יירשו yeirashu אחרים תחתיהם *im meitu yirshu acheirim tachteichem*. However, let's
say he says, "Look,
that is what I want the... you know my son to get
as a weekly allowance. However, if God forbid my children die, what
do you do with that money set aside for their weekly... weekly
allowance?" So then in that case, so...
if they die... I'm sorry, wait wait, let me just make sure
I got this right. Hold on. One
minute. Oh yeah, yeah. So he basically is saying like this, look,
not from the weekly allowance but he's basically saying like this, look.
After my kids die, here I am leaving aside all this money.
From this money I want you to give them a weekly allowance.
After they die, I want the balance of that money to go
to ראובן Reuven *Reuven*. Okay. ראובן Reuven *Reuven*... not my son. ראובן
Reuven *Reuven* and שמעון Shimon *Shimon*. Okay. So in that case because
I want ראובן Reuven *Reuven* and שמעון Shimon *Shimon* to get the
balance of what's left, you assume that even when I say שקל
shekel *shekel* I didn't mean at least a שקל shekel *shekel*, I
meant exactly a שקל shekel *shekel* because I am concerned if my
kids... the ones that are going to inherit it afterwards, so eventually
it's going to be their money anyway, okay. So שקל was like
an estimate; if they need more, give them more, okay. But if
I want ראובן Reuven or שמעון Shimon to get it afterwards, then
when I say שקל I mean exactly a שקל because I care
what ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon, get and I want—if there's anything
left over. I understand, but I also did say—I also did say
a שקל. So the second that we gave the executor latitude to
interpret a שקל before as at least a שקל, right, that made
sense when—when the kids were going to eventually inherit the balance anyway.
But if the kids aren't going to inherit the balance, you are
the one who was upset about the latitude we gave the guy.
Exactly. So he could have said it differently, he could have said—I
understand, but anyway, that's how we interpret in this context. Okay, בין
שאמר תנו בין שאמר אל תתנו, Bein she’amar tenu, bein she’amar al
titnu, whether he says give them a שקל or whether he says
give them no more than a שקל, אינו נותן אלא שקל. Eino
noten ela shekel. Since somebody else is going to inherit the balance,
we're going to interpret the word שקל to mean exactly a שקל,
not at least a שקל. Yes. If—if his children had children, then
is he allowed to say—in other words, if he's—if he's saying it
as a gift—if
my—if my children die, I want to give my money to this
other person and not their children? Yes, correct. And because it's his
property, meaning if he just died and said nothing, then his kids
would inherit him, they would die, it would pass on to their
kids. But because right now on this guy's—let's—let's say it's a שכיב
מרע shechiv mera bequest, that fits into the context of what we're
doing. Let's say it's a שכיב מרע shechiv mera bequest. He could
just say, I'm going to give all of it to ראובן Reuven
and שמעון Shimon who aren't his kids. He could also say, I'm
going to set it aside as a fund for my kids, and
after they die, I'm going to give it to ראובן Reuven and
שמעון, Shimon right? And that's what he's doing. So since that's—right, and
he's able to because he could avoid the whole natural path of
ירושה. yerusha. Okay, so that's what he's doing. Now, so that's a
type of a שכיב מרע shechiv mera bequest. Now, here's why this
is relevant for us: והכא דכי שתי שדות ובשני בני אדם דמי.
Vehacha dechi shetei sadot uvishenei benei adam dami.
You have his kids and you have ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon
who are going to get it after his kids. When he's talking
about his kids, he says, give to my kids a שקל a
week in this fund and this money I set aside. And then
he says, but when my kids die, ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon
should inherit the balance. Notice the first word on this עמוד ב:
amud bet:
ירשו אחרים תחתיהם. Yirshu acherim tachteihem. So he said give it to
my kids, and when they die, let ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon
inherit the balance. All right, so that's two—two people, kids and whatever;
kids he used the word מתנה, matana, the others he used the
word inherit. Now, is it two fields or one field? So conceptually,
you could say one field, it's this fund and this money set
aside. Although here you could certainly say that it's two fields because
the stuff the kids get is not the stuff the others are
inheriting, right? I mean, if here's your big pile of money, you
know what I mean, and the kids are going to get this
part of it, okay, because
that's the amount that's going to go out to them and there's
all this money's going to be left over, the stuff that the
others are going to get—I mean, they're going to get from the
money that's in the fund, but they are going to get something
different than the kids get. The kids get that part and then
the rest is what's left over. Okay, the גמרא's Gemara going to
even—even have—another case that's going to sound even more like one field
that it's going to claim as like two fields. But that's his
argument, okay? My kids are getting X, ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon.
are getting Y, and by my kids I say give and ראובן
Reuven and שמעון Shimon I say ירושה, yerusha, and we're going to
give it to ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon Why? I said ירושה.
yerusha. It must be we use the word מתנה matana I said
when referring to my kids to interpret that even to ראובן Reuven
and שמעון Shimon I'm giving it as a gift and not as
a ירושה. yerusha. What if his kids don't die? Well, eventually they'll
die. No, but the man dies, right? Yeah. And then the kids
are living, right? And they keep on getting it? The rest of—they
only get a שקל a week? No, they keep on getting a
שקל a week. He left over this money as a fund, and
here's what he wants to be done with this fund. This is
what he's doing. He's not just dying and letting them inherit it.
On his deathbed he is saying, take all this money, this million
dollars, put it in this fund, give my kids a weekly allowance
of fifty dollars a week, and any money in that fund that's
left over after they die, ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon. should inherit.
If they die, do their heirs get it? That's an interesting question,
I don't know, we'll get to that later. But at least his
point is—yeah, it's different people, different fields, and it works. Right, that's
what he says. So you see, even if you use for one
person, the kids get a לשון מתנה lashon matana and ראובן Reuven
and שמעון Shimon get a לשון ירושה, lashon yerusha, we're still going
to give it to ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon We're פוסקין poskin
like—exactly like—exactly—like רבנן Rabbanan or like רב ששת? Rav Sheshet? Correct. Yeah,
okay,
yeah.
Okay, and at the time he's doing it, you don't know how
much the kids are going to get. Correct, correct. And conceptually you
could call this one field, certainly, because it's one fund, but the
גמרא's Gemara choosing—he's choosing to call it two fields and say this
is evidence of my position. Okay. והכא דכי שתי שדות ובשני בני
אדם דמי, Vehacha dechi shetei sadot uvishenei benei adam dami, דקתני דקני,
dekatani dekani,
and we say that it works. The גמרא Gemara says, הוה מותיב
לה והוא מפרק לה. Hu motiv lah vehu mefarek lah. He used
this as a challenge and he— to challenge his opposing positions to
prove his side but he also you know sort of explains it
meaning he's able you know or solves it meaning he's able to
sort of offer a defense for those who would not agree with
him. What would the defense be for those who would not agree
with him? בראוי ליורשו רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה. be'raui l'yorsho Rabbi Yochanan
ben Broka. So this is a this is a little bit of
a cheat answer okay so here are
okay here are his sons okay and he says give it to
them תנתן שקל tinaten shekel and then he says and the remainder
you know ראובן ושמעון Reuven u'Shimon here should be you know
יירשו they should inherit okay אחר. acher. So what it's saying is
ah look the לשון ירושה lashon yerusha works why does לשון ירושה
lashon yerusha work it must be we borrow the לשון מתנה lashon
matana and apply it to here. So he says wait maybe this
ראובן ושמעון Reuven u'Shimon are actually his relatives as well okay maybe
they're his grandkids maybe they're his brothers you know his cousins and
there's a position of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka
that we're going to get to as we've mentioned before that says
that you are allowed to reassign and redistribute amongst your heirs okay
remember we quoted that before that רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yochanan
ben Broka so he says the reason the language of ירושה yerusha
works here is not because we're borrowing the language of מתנה matana
from the sons it's that according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi
Yochanan ben Broka the language of ירושה yerusha works if you use
it for people that are in a line of inheritance now we're
going to deal with exactly where they have to be in that
line okay so the גמרא Gemara is saying maybe this has nothing
to do with borrowing the language of מתנה matana maybe it works
because ראובן ושמעון Reuven u'Shimon are in a line of inheritance and
for רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka you can use
the language ירושה yerusha for somebody who's in the line of inheritance
okay good so now the גמרא Gemara continues אמר רב אשי amar
Rav Ashi so we're still going to try to prove it says
רב אשי Rav Ashi תא שמע ta shema come and hear here's
another case where it seems like you use a language ירושה yerusha
and it works because you're borrowing the language of מתנה matana even
like two fields and two people נכסי לך ואחריך יירש פלוני ואחרי
אחריך יירש פלוני nechasai lach ve'achareicha yeirash ploni ve'acharei achareicha yeirash ploni
okay
so here it is here's a guy on his deathbed okay here
we'll draw the guy on his deathbed okay anyway okay I don't
know anyway okay I don't know what looks like almost like he's
on his funeral bier okay whatever anyway here's a guy on his
deathbed and he says okay he says
נכסי לך
ואחריך
פלוני nechasai lach ve'achareicha ploni
and etc okay so basically this guy says right first who gets
my property
this is his property okay so he makes a three-way given he
says first it goes to this guy לך lach that'll be you
okay then he says what he says ואחריך יירש פלוני ve'achareicha yeirash
ploni okay and after let's say the first guy is ראובן Reuven's
and then שמעון Shimon and then לוי Levi they're not brothers okay
so he says first to you
so לך lach then he says ואחריך יירש פלוני ve'achareicha yeirash ploni
יירש yeirash notice the לשון lashon of ירושה yerusha right and then
what does it say ואחריך יירש ואחרי
אחריך יירש פלוני ve'achareicha yeirash ve'acharei achareicha yeirash ploni and after him
לוי Levi will יירש yeirash will inherit it so to you is
going to be read as a language of מתנה matana just you
get it that's like מתנה matana so after you שמעון Shimon and
after שמעון Shimon then לוי Levi inherit so notice he's saying inherit
inherit and we're going to say it goes from ראובן Reuven to
שמעון Shimon to לוי Levi okay so look why is it why
does the לשון ירושה lashon yerusha work it must be we borrow
the language of מתנה matana even though they're different people now this
however sounds like different people and what the same field or a
different field
same field ראובן Reuven get it and after ראובן Reuven שמעון Shimon's
gets it so it's really shouldn't be much of a proof we're
talking about the same field okay but the גמרא Gemara is going
to say
since
שמעון Shimon never owns it during ראובן Reuven lifetime and לוי Levi
never owns it during שמעון Shimon lifetime it's like it's different fields
there's never any period in time where they're jointly owning it so
since that's true it's like a case of different fields and if
we apply the מתנה matana from ראובן Reuven to שמעון Shimon even
though they're not owning it at the same time you see that
even different people and different fields even though it's not technically a
different field we can use the לשון מתנה lashon matana to go
from one to the next all right now obviously this is easy
to argue on and say that this is effectively the same field
but that's
Well, they only used the word לך. lecha. That's another חידוש chiddush
that we're even going to use the word this is yours is
effectively לשון מתנה lashon matana because it's not לשון ירושה. lashon yerusha.
Okay, so שכיב מרע שאמר נכסיי לפלוני ואחריו לפלוני, shchiv meira she-amar
nechasai le-Ploni ve-acharav le-Ploni, מת ראשון קנה שני, met rishon kana sheini,
then it works. After Reuven dies, Shimon gets it. מת שני קנה
שלישי, met sheini kana shelishi, after Shimon dies, Levi gets it. ומת
שני בחיי ראשון, u-meit sheini be-chayei rishon, now Shimon died before Reuven
died.
So after Reuven dies, יחזרו נכסים ליורשי ראשון. yachzoru nechasim le-yorshei rishon.
So
if once the chain is broken, it's broken. So after Reuven dies,
if Shimon isn't around to get it, then then that sort of
chain cannot be satisfied, so it doesn't jump over to Levi. Then
it just doesn't continue. If it doesn't continue, then after Reuven died,
Reuven's heirs get it because this thing like if if if it
can't work the way he said, it just stops where it is.
Okay, so that's that הלכה. halacha. That's not of interest to us,
but that is the הלכה halacha there. Okay. מת שני קנה... wait
a minute, no, ליורשי ראשון. והכא, ve-hacha,
now that's the teaching. Now the גמרא Gemara says the following: והכא,
ve-hacha, now in this case, דכשתי שדות ושני בני אדם דמי. de-kishtei
sadot u-shnei bnei adam dami. It's like two fields and two people.
So two people it definitely is. Why two fields? Since they're not
owning it at the same time, we're treating it like two fields.
וקתני דקנה, ve-katani de-kana,
and look, Shimon gets it and Levi gets it. So you see
that the language of מתנה matana that we say to one person
can we borrow and apply to another person even in a case
of separate people and presumably separate fields if this is enough like
separate fields. So once again, a proof that we can use that
language from even two people and two fields. וכי תימא, ve-chi teima,
now let's say you try to answer, הכא נמי בראוי ליורשו ורבי
יוחנן בן ברוקה. hacha nami be-rauy le-yorsho ve-Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. Ah,
wait, the גמרא Gemara says maybe we'll have the same answer we
had before. Maybe Shimon and Levi are this guy, are heirs to
this guy who's dying. So the language of ירושה yerusha works not
because we're borrowing the language of מתנה. matana. The language of ירושה
yerusha works 'cause he can give it to them with a language
of ירושה yerusha because they're in line to inherit and we're ruling
like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה. Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. Same answer we
gave before, okay. So maybe it has nothing to do with the
language of מתנה, matana, maybe the language of ירושה yerusha can work.
הכא נמי בראוי
ליורשו ורבי יוחנן בן ברוקה היא. hacha nami be-rauy le-yorsho ve-Rabbi Yochanan
ben Beroka hi. אי הכי, ei hachi, if that was true, מת
שני קנה שלישי, met sheini kana shelishi, then why when Shimon would
die would it go to Levi? Why not? הא שלח רב אחא
בריה דרב אויא לרב יוחנן, ha shalach Rav Acha brei de-Rav Avya
le-Rav Yochanan, הא שלח רב אחא בריה דרב אויא, ha shalach Rav
Acha brei de-Rav Avya, Rav Acha the son of Rav Avya sent
the following message: לדברי רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה, le-divrei Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka, נכסיי לך ואחריך לפלוני, nechasai lecha ve-acharecha le-ploni,
if I'm going to say I'm going to let Reuven inherit it
and this is according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka that you can reassign inheritance to heirs, right? And after Reuven
let Shimon inherit it, or or you just say give it to
Reuven and after Reuven to Shimon, וראשון ראוי ליורשו, ve-rishon rauy le-yorsho,
and the first one is an heir, אין לשני במקום ראשון כלום,
ein le-sheini bi-mkom rishon klum, then Shimon gets nothing. שאין זה לשון
מתנה אלא לשון ירושה, she-ein ze lashon matana ela lashon yerusha,
since Reuven was fit to inherit, even if you said give it,
you know, let Reuven get it, we interpret that as let him
inherit. וירושה אין לה הפסק, ve-yerusha ein la hefsek,
and an inheritance does not interrupt it. What does that mean? It
means the following. It means that
let's say let's say Reuven here, according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה,
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, let's say Reuven was an heir, okay? And
he said give it to Reuven. So now there's a double חידוש
chiddush of what we're about to say according to רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקה. Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. Even though he said give it to
Reuven, it's like the opposite, right? Until now we've been saying as
long as you have that language of מתנה matana we're going to
jump on it and use it in order to make it good,
right? Now according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka,
he says that if somebody's in a line of inheritance, you can
actually reassign a ירושה. yerusha. So according to that, even if you
don't use a language of ירושה, yerusha, if you say give it
to Reuven and Reuven's in a line of inheritance, because of that
we're going to interpret it as you saying I'm assigning the ירושה
yerusha to Reuven. So it's almost like the mirror image, right? Since
it works to say ירושה yerusha when somebody's in a line of
inheritance, we're going to automatically interpret, I mean, I guess if you
said if I'm gifting it to Reuven you were explicit, maybe we
would say it was a gift, but if you say give it
to Reuven, we're going to interpret that as I'm assigning Reuven as
my heir since that's what works according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה.
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. So that's חידוש chiddush number one. You say
I'm I'm giving it to Reuven, it means I'm assigning him as
my heir which works for רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka if he's in a line of inheritance. Now let's say you
said after Reuven I want Shimon to get it, okay, and I
want Shimon either to get it or to inherit it, whatever you
said. It's not going to work. You know why it's not going
to work? Even though Shimon is also in your line of inheritance,
because once Reuven is an heir, after an heir gets it, it's
totally his. You can only reassign property that you're gifting to somebody.
You get it for so long, after you get it somebody else
is going to get it. But if ראובן Reuven generally inherited it,
something you inherit, somebody the person who died can't stipulate that you're
not going to get it after a certain period of time. So
once you assigned ראובן Reuven. as your heir, you can't say after
he died it goes somewhere else. Once he gets it, then after
he died it's going to go to his heirs because he got
it as an heir. This is according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא.
Rebbe Yochanan ben Broka. It's the exact opposite of the מתנה matana
approach according to the חכמים. Chachamim. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara is
saying that if that were true, if this were going according to
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rebbe Yochanan ben Broka and the language of
ירושה yerusha here worked, not because we were borrowing the language of
מתנה. matana. The language of ירושה yerusha works because שמעון Shimon and
לוי Levi were in line to inherit. If that were true, okay,
then after שמעון Shimon died it would not go to לוי. Levi.
Once שמעון Shimon. was assigned as an heir, after he died it
would go to his heirs. Okay?
So is that clear? You cannot say that the language ירושה yerusha
here works according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא. Rebbe Yochanan ben Broka.
Because according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rebbe Yochanan ben Broka, if
the language ירושה yerusha worked because שמעון Shimon was in line to
inherit, you could not determine where it would go after שמעון. Shimon's
Once שמעון Shimon was an heir, it would stay within שמעון's Shimon
family. All right, so therefore it must be we're not going according
to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא. Rebbe Yochanan ben Broka. We're going that
according to the חכמים Chachamim and the only reason ירושה yerusha works
is because it's borrowing from the language of מתנה matana up here.
And once that's true, you see that the language of מתנה matana
can redefine even two fields and two people.
People get it? More or less? Yeah? Okay. So let's read that
let's read that again. וכי
תימא, Vechi teima, I'm going back to וכי תימא. vechi teima. וכי
תימא, Vechi teima, if you say: הכא נמי בראוי
ליורשו, Hacha nami berauy leyorsho, maybe the reason here שמעון Shimon and
לוי Levi get it is because they're in line to inherit and
it's not because of using the language of מתנה. matana. בראוי ליורשו
Berauy leyorsho ורבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא היא. veRebbe Yochanan ben Broka hi. No. אי הכי, Ei
hachi, if we were talking about שמעון Shimon and לוי Levi were
in line to
inherit, why when שמעון Shimon's would die would it go on to
לוי? Levi? שמעון Shimon. would be a real heir according to רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא Rebbe Yochanan ben Broka and then it wouldn't go
on, it would stay within שמעון's Shimon family. השלח ליה רבה בר
רב אדא לרב יוסף, Hashlach lei Rabbah bar Rav Adda leRav Yosef,
Rabbah the son of Rav Adda sent to Rav Yosef: לדידי רבי
יוחנן, Ledidi Rebbe Yochanan, according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rebbe Yochanan
ben Broka, נכסי לך ואחריך לפלוני, nechasai lach veacharecha leploni,
I'm giving it to you and after you I'm giving it to,
I'm giving it to ראובן Reuven and after ראובן Reuven to שמעון.
Shimon, וראשון ראוי ליורשו Verishon rauy leyorsho and ראובן Reuven is actually
an heir. אין לשני במקום ראשון כלום, Ein lashani bemakom rishon klum,
that שמעון Shimon gets nothing. שאין זה לשון מתנה אלא לשון ירושה,
She'ein ze lashon matana ella lashon yerusha, even though he didn't explicitly
say ירושה, yerusha, he just said I'm giving it to ראובן. Reuven's
Since ראובן Reuven is an heir, we're going to read it as
a language of ירושה, yerusha, as designating ראובן Reuven as an heir.
וירושה אין לה הפסק Veyerusha ein la hefsek and once ראובן Reuven
gets it as an heir, it doesn't go somewhere else, it passes
down to ראובן's Reuven kids. So this cannot be רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא Rebbe Yochanan ben Broka because רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rebbe Yochanan
ben Broka once somebody is an heir and you designate that it's
going to them, you cannot control where it goes afterwards, it stays
within their family. So this must be חכמים Chachamim and the language
of ירושה yerusha works because we're borrowing the language of מתנה. matana.
So you see even שני בני אדם shenei benei adam and we're
going to consider it like two fields although it's not really, you
borrow language of מתנה matana to interpret the language of ירושה. yerusha.
אלא תיובתא דכולהו תיובתא. Ella tyuvta dechulehu tyuvta. This is a contradiction
to everybody. This shows, I mean everybody who's not the most lenient
opinion, right? Even different fields and different people, you borrow the language
of מתנה. matana. Because that's clearly what you're doing in this case.
So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא נמי תהוי תיובתא דריש לקיש. Leima
nami tehei tyuvta deResh Lakish. Now let this also be a contradiction
of ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. Remember ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said it
only works if you package it all
together. Let it be a gift to my two fields to ראובן
Reuven and שמעון, Shimon let them inherit it and let it be
a gift and let them inherit. Right? It sounds like normally two
fields and two people wouldn't work according to ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
unless you really packaged it all nice and tightly together. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ותסברא, Vetisbra, does that make sense that we would
reject ריש לקיש? Resh Lakish? והאמר רבא, Veha'amar Rava, Rava says: הלכתא
כוותיה דריש לקיש בהני תלת. Hilchata kevateih deResh Lakish behani telat. We
rule like ריש לקיש Resh Lakish in three cases. And one of
those three cases is our case, that if you say different people
and different fields, you have to package it tightly together. How does
that work together with this ruling that different people and different fields
it works, you can borrow from one to the next? So the
גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, Lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן בתוך
כדי דיבור כאן לאחר כדי דיבור. Kan betoch kedei dibbur kan leachar
kedei dibbur. How
when you said those two things, that ראובן Reuven get the field
and let שמעון Shimon. inherit this other field,
and we're going to use the language of give to interpret the
language of inherit, that's only if you said those two things... statements
תוך כדי דיבור. toch kedei dibbur. תוך כדי דיבור Toch kedei dibbur
is the time it takes to say, Peace be upon you, my
master. Okay, like when you greet somebody?
So, like what is it? Like a second. Okay, so if the
statement number two starts within תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur statement
number one, we interpret it all as one statement. But if there
was enough of a pause between statement number two and statement number
one, then they are not interpreted as one statement and we can't
borrow a language of gift and apply it to the other statement
that has the language of ירושה. yerusha. Okay, so basically when did
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish say when do we borrow from one to
the other? If there was תוך כדי דיבור. toch kedei dibbur. If
the statement that has the ירושה yerusha line in it and the
statement that has the מתנה matana line in it... the words ירושה
yerusha and מתנה matana don't have to be תוך כדי דיבור. toch
kedei dibbur. The two statements have to be, right? The giving to
ראובן where that sentence ends: let ראובן inherit field X. Right, that
sentence ended with the word field X. And then the next sentence
is: and let שמעון Shimon and give field Y to שמעון. Shimon
So between the ending of sentence one and the beginning of sentence
two (sentence one was about ראובן and sentence two was about שמעון),
Shimon there can't be more than תוך כדי דיבור. toch kedei dibbur.
There can't be more than one or two seconds. If it's within
that time, it's all one big statement and we use the word
give to interpret the other word. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says even
if the two statements are separated by תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei
dibbur, if you package them all together in that language of ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish, that's when it works. So when does ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish say you have to package it all together? When they're
separated by תוך כדי דיבור. toch kedei dibbur. But if they're within
תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, you can use the language of
מתנה matana to explain the language of ירושה. yerusha. Okay, and now
the
גמרא Gemara says: כאן בתוך כדי דיבור כאן לאחר כדי דיבור. Kan
betoch kedei dibbur kan le'achar kedei dibbur. והלכתא והלכה
היא: Ve-hilcheta ve-halacha hi: כל תוך כדי דיבור כדיבור דמי. kol toch
kedei dibbur ke-dibbur dami. Anytime something is within the period it takes
to, תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, we interpret it as one
statement.
לבר מעבודה זרה וקידושין, Levar me'avoda zara ve-kiddushin, except for idolatry and
קידושין. kiddushin. So in the case of idolatry, somebody basically turns to
an idol and says, I accept you as my god. Okay, and
then says, Ah, just kidding! No, I don't mean it. I take
it back. Okay, we say no, idolatry is so weighty and serious
that
there's no retracting even within a few seconds. That was a statement
of idolatry and punishable accordingly even if it was retracted. The גמרא
Gemara also has a similar example of blasphemy. If somebody blasphemes God
and then retracts it within תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, the
retraction doesn't help. The statement is so weighty that
there's no period to rethink and reconsider.
Similarly, קידושין, kiddushin, if somebody says to a woman, הרי את מקודשת
לי בטבעת זו, Harei at mekudeshet li be-taba'at zo, and then says,
Just kidding! Okay, right?
That does not work. Now that's actually interesting because sometimes there is
some areas of תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur by קידושין kiddushin
that we use to interpret the context of the words of which
something is said. Like somebody says to a woman, Would you like
to marry me? and she says, Yes. And then he says, Oh,
here's this ring. So now he didn't say in the giving of
the ring like הרי את מקודשת לי, Harei at mekudeshet li, but
maybe there actually we even say more... the גמרא Gemara in קידושין
Kiddushin says even עסוקין באותו ענין, asukin be-oto inyan, even not תוך
כדי דיבור. toch kedei dibbur. Even if we've just been in the
middle of a long conversation about getting married, and I didn't say
the words... we were sitting on the couch and we were talking
about, So, what do you think? Do you think it'll be July?
Maybe August? Whatever, maybe we should do it sooner. And we're sitting
and we took a little drink of our tea or whatever and
a minute... say, Oh, you know what? Here, just take this ring.
Okay, so even though it wasn't תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur,
since that was the context, we interpret that as an act of
קידושין. kiddushin. But this is more probably a case where you're retracting.
We're not using the context to clarify; you're retracting. And we say
that something that's that weighty, if you try to
retract, it's too late. Once it's done, it's done. You don't get
a chance to reconsider after you like pull the string as it
were. Okay, so that's עבודה זרה avoda zara and קידושין, kiddushin, and
another גמרא Gemara also says גירושין geirushin would be similar. So that's
interesting cases where we limit the role of תוך כדי דיבור. toch
kedei dibbur. Now, wait... Where do you need witnesses though? What? You
need witnesses? Yeah, you need witnesses in גט get and קידושין. kiddushin.
And עבודה זרה avoda zara if we want to punish somebody, sure.
Sure, but then there's still a question: what were you doing? Were
you able to retract? But if they're sitting on the couch having
tea, they have to have a witness there. Yeah, exactly. Now... now,
now, what is the idea of תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur,
right? Is it a biblical idea or a rabbinic idea? There's a
famous תוספות. Tosafot. If you take a look at this early תוספות,
Tosafot, והלכתא תוך כדי דיבור כדיבור דמי, Ve-hilcheta toch kedei dibbur ke-dibbur
dami, I'll just read it to you. תוספות Tosafot says: פירש רבנו
תם דלהכי אמר כדיבור דמי כדי שאילת תלמיד לרב היינו שלום עליך
רבי לפי שכשאדם עושה
סחורה עם חבירו ויהיה רבו או גדול ממנו בחכמה לא יתן לו
שלום שאם יתן לו שלום לא יוכל לחזור בו ממקחו ובכך תיקנו
חכמים שכשעור זה יכול לחזור. Perish Rabbeinu Tam de-lehachi amar ke-dibbur dami
kedei she'ilat talmid le-rav hainu shalom alecha rabbi lefi she-kesh-adam oseh sechorah
im chaveiro ve-yiheh rabbo o gadol mimmeno be-chochmah lo yiten lo shalom
she-im yiten lo shalom lo yuchal lachzor bo mi-mikcho u-be-kach tiknu chachamim
she-keshiur zeh yachol lachzor. So he says, רבנו תם... Rabbeinu Tam... business
with Gloria and I'm about to buy her car and we say
like okay how much a thousand dollars whatever good shake on it
and then just at that moment you know my friend or my
rabbi or whatever passes and I was like oh שלום עליכם רבי
Shalom aleichem rebbi and then I turn back like wait you know
what I had a second oh too late it was two seconds
between you know you know the deal's final cause so then so
because I wouldn't want her to say that I would have to
ignore and be impolite to my rebbi who passed by because as
soon as I return to say hi I would lose my opportunity
to you know to redefine the terms of what we're working out.
So in order to not have that case of being like impolite
or rude or whatever offending you know an important person we allow
you to say hello and to still turn back and be in
the middle of a deal. Very interesting logic behind it. The problem
תוספות Tosafot has is is that it seems from other cases that
תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur works in a wide range of
cases that have nothing to do with doing business deals and interrupting
and saying hello and it's just part of a definition of how
do we define things taking place at the same time or you
know what is considered enough that it's or when do we consider
your דעת da'at you know your your intent is still in the
sort of in the process and when is it complete? Like if
you know that often happens like you're thinking it through you're saying
something but as you're saying it you're still reconsidering it like to
give a few seconds to say like that's it your דעת da'at
is final. So it doesn't seem like it's just this Rabbinic idea
of not you know instituted to prevent people from being rude. There's
other ways of understanding it. That's number one. Number two though is
רשב"ם Rashbam points out
like there's a wide range of possibilities of what it means when
we say things happened at the same time. It happens at the
same time but let's say you're saying different things. So he says
the following scenarios: let's say both things are possible. You say this
animal is an עולה olah and a שלמים. shlamim. So which is
it? So you it's half עולה olah half שלמים shlamim obviously it
can't be either as a קרבן korban but you know you would
redeem the value and use half the money for an עולה olah
half for a שלמים. shlamim. So that's תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei
dibbur when both of them can be satisfied. You some way do
sort of like both. Then there's another case in which you say
תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur one interprets the other. Like you
say ירושה yerusha and מתנה matana like we're dealing with. Okay? The
reason that רשב"ם Rashbam says you allow the word מתנה matana to
interpret the word ירושה yerusha is that the word ירושה yerusha has
no halachic effect and the word מתנה matana does. So the word
מתנה matana will dominate if they're within תוך כדי דיבור. toch kedei
dibbur. Says then you've got a scenario where they're contradictory where you're
sort of saying two very contradict- and this is what Michael was
asking two very contradictory statements and you say it תוך כדי דיבור.
toch kedei dibbur. I'm giving all of this to ראובן to שמעון
Shimon you know no I'm giving all of it to שמעון well
which one? You know do you say תפוס לשון ראשון tfos lashon
rishon or תפוס לשון אחרון? tfos lashon acharon? Okay they were said
at the same moment so which one dominates? So there there's a
whole range of opinions which one you go by. He says but
certainly if it's clear that what you're doing is retracting you say
you know no I'm giving to- no no no to שמעון right
then everybody says a retraction תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur works.
But if it's not a retraction it's just two parts of a
statement or contradictory or whatever and then we have to say they
happened at the same time then you need certain rules of how
to interpret which part of those statements are going to be true
and which ones are going to dominate. Okay and that's that question
of even by saying תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur is כדיבור
דמי kedibbur dami it doesn't always tell you how you're going to
interpret the statement. You're just going to sort of say it's not
like it was done when you got the first word out of
your mouth. We're interpreting it as one big statement. In our case
we interpret ירושה yerusha by the word מתנה matana because ירושה yerusha
are just non-effective words. They're meaning- they won't have any effect. So
we'll use the word מתנה matana to dominate and to interpret the
whole statement. Also as I said earlier clearly we want to allow
this person to give a מתנה matana so we're going to be
more liberal in reading it that way. Okay we will end with
this.